



🛘 +47 41 66 82 18 | 🔀 vegard.lysne@gmail.com | 🌴 www.vegardlysne.no | 🛅 vegard-lysne | 💆 VegardLysne

Professional summary

I'm a clinical dietitian (PhD), working as a postdoctoral researcher at Haukeland University Hospital. My main professional interests are methods in nutritional epidemiology and statistics, including programming in the R language, data reporting, and visualization. Currently I'm the primary investigator of the Postprandial Metabolism in Healthy Young Subjects (PoMet) study (ClinicalTrials.gov: NCT04989478). I hold positions as editorial board member of the Norwegian Journal of Nutrition, review editor in Frontiers in Nutrition, member of the Norwegian Scientific Committee for Food and Environment (VKM), the Scientific Panel on Nutrition, Dietetic Products, Novel Food and Allergy, and chapter expert on riboflavin, niacin, and vitamin B12 in the Nordic Nutrition Recommendations 2022. Starting in 2022, I'm involved in th organization committee of NUTRINOR, a national research school in nutrition, funded by the Research Council of Norway until 2030.

Education

PhD Norway

DEPARTMENT OF CLINICAL SCIENCE, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN

2015-2019

 Thesis title: Biomarkers of one-carbon metabolism and B-vitamin status - Targeted metabolomics in rats and humans exploring the effects of PPAR alpha-activation and dietary composition

MSc, Clinical Nutrition Norway

University of Bergen, Faculty of Medicine

2012-2014

 Thesis title: Treatment with a Peroxisome Proliferator-Activated Receptor agonist influences one-carbon metabolism and markers of B-vitamin status in rats

BSc, Human Nutriton Norway

University of Bergen, Faculty of Medicine

2009-2012

Work experience _____

Postdoctoral researcher

DEPARTMENT OF HEART DISEASE, HAUKELAND UNIVERSITY HOSPITAL, BERGEN, NORWAY

2020-

Researcher

DEPARTMENT OF CLINICAL SCIENCE, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN, BERGEN, NORWAY

2019

PhD candidate

DEPARTMENT OF CLINICAL SCIENCE, UNIVERSITY OF BERGEN, BERGEN, NORWAY

2015-2019

Research assistant

DEPARTMENT OF HEART DISEASE, HAUKELAND UNIVERSITY HOSPITAL, BERGEN, NORWAY

2014-2015

Courses attended

2016

ENLP Essentials 2021 Building Tidy Tools, RStudio::conf workshop 2019 Data Science in the Tidyverse, RStudio::conf workshop 2018 Competing Risks, Introduction to Flexible Parametric Survival Analysis and Cancer Screening, EPINOR 2017 annual meeting 2017 New statistical methods for causal inference, University of Oslo 2017 Logistic regression, survival analysis and Cox-regression, University of Oslo The Art of Scientific Investigation, EPINOR summer school 2017 University pedagogy for PhD candidates, University of Bergen 2017 2017 Epidemiology - beyond the basics, University of Oslo 6th International course in Nutritional Epidemiology, Imperial College, London 2016 2016 Experimental Design and Statistical Analysis, FRAME training school

Publications in international peer-reviewed journals

Basic course in Medical and Health Related Research, University of Bergen

- 1. **Lysne V**, Anfinsen ÅM, Van Parys A. Should we all adopt the Dietary Approach to Stop Hypertension (DASH) diet? Eur J Prev Cardiol. 2022
- 2. Van Parys A, Brække MS, Karlsson T, Vinknes KJ, Tell GS, Haugsgjerd TR, Ueland PM, Øyen J, Dierkes J, Nygård O, **Lysne V**. Assessment of Dietary Choline Intake, Contributing Food Items and Associations with One-carbon and Lipid Metabolites in Middle-aged and Elderly Adults: The Hordaland Health Study. Front Nutr, 2021. PMID: 34643705
- 3. Hilvo M, Dhar I, Lääperi M, **Lysne V**, Sulo G, Tell GS, Jousilahti P, Nygård OK, Brenner H, Schöttker B, Laaksonen R. Primary cardiovascular risk prediction by LDL-cholesterol in Caucasian middle-aged and older adults: a joint analysis of three cohorts. Eur J Prev Cardiol, 2021. PMID: 34060615
- 4. Van Parys A, Karlsson T, Vinknes KJ, Olsen T, Øyen J, Dierkes J, Nygård O, **Lysne V**. Food Sources Contributing to Intake of Choline and Individual Choline Forms in a Norwegian Cohort of Patients With Stable Angina Pectoris. Front Nutr, 2021. PMID: 34055860
- Saeed S, Vamvakidou A, Zidros S, Papasozomenos G, Lysne, V, Khattar RS, Senior R. Sex differences in transaortic flow rate and association with all-cause mortality in patients with severe aortic stenosis. Eur Heart J Cardiovask Imaging, 2021. PMID: 33734325
- 6. Matre ÅO, Parys AV, Olsen T, Haugsgjerd TR, Baravelli CM, Nygård O, Dierkes J, **Lysne V**. The Association of Meat Intake With All-Cause Mortality and Acute Myocardial Infarction Is Age-Dependent in Patients With Stable Angina Pectoris. Front Nutr, 2021. PMID: 33748176
- 7. Dhar I, Svingen GFT, Olsen T, **Lysne V**, Bjørnestad EØ, Ueland, PM, Nygård, O. β-blocker use and risk of all-cause mortality in patients with coronary heart disease: effect modification by serum vitamin A. Eur J Prev Cardiol, 2021. PMID: 33709106
- 8. Haugsgjerd TR, Egeland GM, Nygård OK, Igland J, Sulo G, **Lysne V**, Vinknes KJ, Bjornevik K, Tell GS. Intake of carbohydrates and SFA and risk of CHD in middle-age adults: the Hordaland Health Study (HUSK). Public Health Nutr, 2020. PMID: 32907659
- 9. Saeed S, Smith J, Grigoryan K, **Lysne V**, Rajani R, Chambers JB. The tricuspid annular plane systolic excursion to systolic pulmonary artery pressure index: Association with all-cause mortality in patients with moderate or severe tricuspid regurgitation. Int J Cardiol, 2020. PMID: 32512064
- 10. Parys AV, **Lysne V**, Øyen J, Dierkes J, Nygård O. No effect of plasma trimethylamine N-Oxide (TMAO) and plasma trimethyllysine (TML) on the association between choline intake and acute myocardial infarction risk in patients with stable angina pectoris. Human Nutrition & Metabolism, 2020. doi: j.hnm.2020.200112
- 11. Haugsgjerd TR, Egeland GM, Nygård OK, Vinknes KJ, Sulo G, **Lysne V**, Igland J and Tell GS. Association of Dietary Vitamin K and Risk of Coronary Heart Disease in Middle-Age Adults: The Hordaland Health Study Cohort. BMJ Open, 2020. PMID: 32444431
- 12. Svenningsson MM, Svingen GFT, **Lysne V**, Ueland PM, Tell GS, Pedersen ER, Dhar I, Nilsen DW and Nygård O. Transsulfuration metabolites and the association with incident atrial fibrillation An observational cohort study among Norwegian patients with stable angina pectoris. Int J Cardiol, 2020. PMID: 32389762
- 13. Dhar I, Siddique S, Pedersen ER, Svingen GFT, **Lysne V**, Olsen T, Nilsen DW, Nordrehaug JE, Midttun Ø, Ueland PM, Tell GS and Nygård O. Lipid parameters and vitamin A modify cardiovascular risk prediction by plasma neopterin. Heart, 2020. PMID: 32398245

- 14. **Lysne V**, Bjørndal B, Grinna ML, Midttun Ø, Ueland PM, Berge RK, Dierkes J, Nygård O and Strand E. Short-term treatment with a peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor α agonist influences plasma one-carbon metabolites and B-vitamin status in rats. PLoS One, 2019. PMID: 31805132
- 15. Parys AV, **Lysne V**, Svingen GFT, Ueland PM, Dhar I, Øyen J, Dierkes J and Nygård O. Dietary choline is related to increased risk of acute myocardial infarction in patients with stable angina pectoris. Biochimie, 2019. PMID: 31707100
- 16. Olsen T, Vinknes KJ, Blomhoff R, **Lysne V**, Midttun Ø, Dhar I, Ueland PM, Svingen GFT, Pedersen ER, Drevon CA, Refsum H, Nygård O. Creatinine, total cysteine and uric acid are associated with serum retinol in patients with cardiovascular disease. Eur J Nutr, 2019. PMID: 31502058
- 17. Strand E, **Lysne V**, Grinna ML, Bohov P, Svardal A, Nygård O, Berge RK, Bjørndal B. Short-Term Activation of Peroxisome Proliferator-Activated Receptors alpha and gamma Induces Tissue-Specific Effects on Lipid Metabolism and Fatty Acid Composition in Male Wistar Rats. PPAR res, 2019. PMID: 31308847
- 18. Ulven SM, Christensen JJ, Nygård O, Svardal A, Leder L, Ottestad I, **Lysne V**, Laupsa-Borge J, Ueland PM, Midttun Ø, Meyer K, McCann A, Andersen LF, Holven KB. Using metabolic profiling and gene expression analyses to explore molecular effects of replacing saturated fat with polyunsaturated fat-a randomized controlled dietary intervention study. Am J Clin Nutr, 2019. PMID: 31051508
- 19. Dhar I, **Lysne V**, Svingen GFT, Ueland PM, Gregory JF, Bønaa KH, Nygård OK. Elevated plasma cystathionine is associated with increased risk of mortality among patients with suspected or established coronary heart disease. Am J Clin Nutr, 2019. PMID: 31005968
- 20. Puaschitz NG, Assmus J, Strand E, Karlsson T, Vinknes KJ, **Lysne V**, Drevon CA, Tell GS, Dierkes J, Nygård O. Adherence to the Healthy Nordic Food Index and the incidence of acute myocardial infarction and mortality among patients with stable angina pectoris. J Hum Nutr Diet, 2019. PMID: 30091209
- 21. Dhar I, Svingen GFT, Ueland PM, **Lysne V**, Svenningsson MM, Tell GS, Nygård OK. Plasma Cystathionine and Risk of Incident Stroke in Patients With Suspected Stable Angina Pectoris. J Am Heart Assoc, 2018. PMID: 30371177
- 22. Bjørndal B, Bruheim I, **Lysne V**, Ramsvik MS, Ueland PM, Nordrehaug JE, Nygård OK, Berge RK. Plasma choline, homocysteine and vitamin status in healthy adults supplemented with krill oil: a pilot study. Scand J Clin Lab Invest, 2018. PMID: 30261756
- 23. Dhar I, **Lysne V**, Seifert R, Svingen GFT, Ueland PM, Nygård OK. Plasma methionine and risk of acute myocardial infarction: Effect modification by established risk factors. Atherosclerosis, 2018. PMID: 29621698
- 24. Strauss P, Marti HP, Beisland C, Scherer A, **Lysne V**, Leh S, Flatberg A, Koch E, Beisvag V, Landolt L, Skogstrand T, Eikrem ØS. Expanding the Utilization of Formalin-Fixed, Paraffin-Embedded Archives: Feasibility of miR-Seq for Disease Exploration and Biomarker Development from Biopsies with Clear Cell Renal Cell Carcinoma. Int J Mol Sci, 2018. PMID: 29534467
- 25. Strand E, Rebnord EW, Flygel MR, **Lysne V**, Svingen GFT, Tell GS, Løland KH, Berge RK, Svardal A, Nygård O, Pedersen ER. Serum Carnitine Metabolites and Incident Type 2 Diabetes Mellitus in Patients With Suspected Stable Angina Pectoris. J Clin Endocrinol Metab, 2018. PMID: 29325058
- 26. DeRatt BN, Ralat MA, **Lysne V**, Tayyari F, Dhar I, Edison AS, Garrett TJ, Midttun Ø, Ueland PM, Nygård OK, Gregory JF 3rd. Metabolomic Evaluation of the Consequences of Plasma Cystathionine Elevation in Adults with Stable Angina Pectoris. J Nutr, 2017. PMID: 28794210
- 27. Hannibal L, **Lysne V**, Bjørke-Monsen AL, Behringer S, Grünert SC, Spiekerkoetter U, Jacobsen DW, Blom HJ. Biomarkers and Algorithms for the Diagnosis of Vitamin B12 Deficiency. Front Mol Biosci, 2016. PMID: 27446930
- 28. **Lysne V**, Strand E, Svingen GF, Bjørndal B, Pedersen ER, Midttun Ø, Olsen T, Ueland PM, Berge RK, Nygård O. Peroxisome Proliferator-Activated Receptor Activation is Associated with Altered Plasma One-Carbon Metabolites and B-Vitamin Status in Rats. Nutrients, 2016. PMID: 26742069
- 29. **Lysne V**, Bjørndal B, Vik R, Nordrehaug JE, Skorve J, Nygård O, Berge RK. A Protein Extract from Chicken Reduces Plasma Homocysteine in Rats. Nutrients, 2015. PMID: 26053618
- 30. Øyen J, Svingen GF, Gjesdal CG, Tell GS, Ueland PM, **Lysne V**, Apalset EM, Meyer K, Vollset SE, Nygård OK. Plasma dimethylglycine, nicotine exposure and risk of low bone mineral density and hip fracture: the Hordaland Health Study. Osteoporos Int, 2015. PMID: 25616506

Other publications.

- 1. Matre ÅO, Dierkes J, **Lysne V**. Ernæringsforskning er ikke som annen forskning. Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2020(2)
- 2. Myklebust-Hansen T, **Lysne V**. FENS 2019: Malnutrition in an obese world European perspective. Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2019(4)

- 3. Matre ÅO, Lysne V. B12-tilskudd uten B12-mangel. Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2019(3).
- 4. **Lysne V**. 12. Internasjonale konferanse om enkarbonmetabolisme, B-vitaminer og homocystein. Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2019(3).
- 5. **Lysne V**, Marienborg I, Olsen T. FASEB-konferanse om folat, vitamin B12 og enkarbonmetabolisme. Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2018(3).
- 6. Lysne V, Olsen T. Feilkilder i ernæringsepidemiologi. Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2018(2).
- 7. **Lysne V**. Glimt fra den 11. internasjonale konferansen om homocystein og enkarbonmetabolisme i Århus. Norsk tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2017(3).
- 8. **Lysne V**, Olsen T. Konfidensintervaller hva kan de fortelle deg? Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2017(1)
- 9. **Lysne V**, Olsen T. P-verdier. Veiledende eller villedende? En simulert studie. Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2016(4).
- 10. Christensen JJ, **Lysne V**. Støtter lørdagsgodt. Den Norske Tannlegeforenings Tidende, 2016(5).
- 11. Olsen T, Lysne V. Ta faget tilbake. Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2015(3).
- 12. Kverneland M, Christensen JJ, **Lysne V**. Lavkarbodietter har kommet for å bli, men hører hjemme i klinikken. Norsk Tidsskrift for Ernæring, 2015(2).

Conference attendance _____

2021	The conference of the Norwegian Association of Clinical Dietitians (KEFF), virtual meeting	
2020	Nordic Nutrition Conference 2020 (virtual)	Poster presentation
2020	Sunn Idrett, Oslo, Norway	Oral presentation
2019	The European Nutrition Conference (FENS), Dublin, Ireland	Poster presentation
2019	12th International Conference on homocysteine and one-carbon metabolism, Tarragona, Spain	Poster presentation
2019	RStudio::conf2019, Austin, TX, USA	
2019	The conference of the Norwegian Association of Clinical Dietitians (KEFF), Bergen, Norway	
2018	FASEB Science research conference: Folic Acid, Vitamin B12 and One Carbon Metabolism, Halifax, Nova	Poster presentation
2010	Scotia, Canada	roster presentation
2018	RStudio::conf, San Diego, CA, USA	
2018	The conference of the Norwegian Association of Clinical Dietitians (KEFF), Kristiansand, Norway	
2017	11th International Conference on homocysteine and one-carbon metabolism, Aarhus, Denmark	Poster presentation
2017	Norwegian Society for Epidemiology conference, Tromsø, Norway	
2017	The conference of the Norwegian Association of Clinical Dietitians (KEFF), Oslo, Norway	Oral presentation
2016	Nordic Nutrition Conference, Gotenburg, Sweden	
2016	FASEB Science research conference: Folic Acid, Vitamin B12 and One Carbon Metabolism, Steamboat	Oral presentation
2016	Springs, CO, USA	Oral presentation
2015	10th International Conference on homocysteine and one-carbon metabolism, Nancy, France	Oral presentation
2015	The conference of the Norwegian Association of Clinical Dietitians (KEFF), Oslo, Norway	
2014	FASEB Science research conference: Folic Acid, Vitamin B12 and One Carbon Metabolism, Steamboat	Poster presentation
2014	Springs, CO, USA	roster presentation
2014	Nordic Congress for Dietitians, Bergen, Norway	
2013	9th International Conference on homocysteine and one-carbon metabolism, Dublin, Ireland	Poster presentation
2013	The conference of the Norwegian Association of Clinical Dietitians (KEFF), Oslo, Norway	
2012	The conference of the Norwegian Association of Clinical Dietitians (KEFF), Oslo, Norway	

Teaching experience _____

In the period 2015-current, I have taught courses at every semester of the bachelor and masters program in clinical nutrition at University of Bergen. I've held lectures on topics such as methods in nutrition research, nutritional biochemistry, food science, micronutrient metabolism, genetic disorders in nutrient metabolism and general nutrition in health and disease.

		• •
Dhn	Candidata	CHINARVICIAN
ГПР	calluluate	supervision

2020-	Anthea Van Parys	Main superviso
2020-	Åslaug O Matre	Main Superviso

Student supervision _____

2021-	Christina Osland Johannesen	MSc
2021-	Mia Mårteig	MSc
2021-	Sunniva Grønnslett	MSc
2021-	Vilde Haugen Myklebust	MSc
2021	Vilde R Strøm	BSo
2020-21	Marianne Braatveit	MSc
2020-21	Marie Kulseth	MSc
2020	Rosemarie Aaby and Ann Helen Børseth	BSc
2019-20	Åslaug O Matre	MSc
2018	Åslaug O Matre and Henriette Holm	BSc
2017-18	Ingvild Marienborg	MSc
2016-17	Jostein Sæle	MSc
2016-17	Kristine S. Samuelsen	MSc
2016-17	Marcela Palma	MSc
2016	Turid Bjørnsen Iversen	BSc
2015	Jostein Sæle, Helene Dahl, Caroline K Jacobsen and Silje S Vabø	BSc

Thesis comittees_____

2021	Sol Bjørkevoll, Stella Rasmussen, Eirin S Gjerde	MSc theses
2021	Hanna H Danielsen, Kristin L Nilsen	BSc theses
2020	Maren T Aase,Andrea H Kalås	MSc theses
2020	Elise Frederich	BSc thesis
2018	Eirin S Gjerde, Emilie H Markhus	BSc theses
2017	Trine Larsen, Helene Søiland, Miriam H Brandt	MSc theses
2017	Amalie Moxness, Maria-Anna F Holmefjord, Benedicte Wirkola	BSc theses
2016	Tonje N Hustoft, Anita E Smette	MSc theses
2016	Synnøve Næss, Ingrid Revheim, Charlotte Z Tøssebro, Renate D Laumann	BSc theses
2015	Anette Hetlevik, Maria B Songve	BSc theses

Organizations and comittees _____

2021-	Member of the Norwegian Scientific Committee for Food and Environment (VKM), the Scientific Panel on
	Nutrition, Dietetic Products, Novel Food and Allergy
2020-	Nordic Nutrition Recommendations 2022, Chapter author, Cobalamin
2020-	Nordic Nutrition Recommendations 2022, Chapter author, Niacin
2020-	Nordic Nutrition Recommendations 2022, Chapter author, Riboflavin
2020-	Review Editor, Frontiers in Nutrition
2019	Leader of the Organizing comittee of the annual conference of The Norwegian Association of Dietitians
2018-	Member of the editorial board, Norwegian Journal of Nutrition (NTFE)
015-2018	Member of the academic policy board, The Norwegian Association of Dietitians affilliated with The
	Norwegian Association of Researchers

Skills and languages

R/Rstudio: Statistical programming, data handling and visualization

SPSS: Statistical software STATA: Statistical software

Microsoft Office: Word, Excel, Powerpoint, Outlook

Inkscape: Vector graphics Git/GitHub: Version control Norwegian, Written and oral English, Written and oral Experienced
Experienced
Basic knowledge
Experienced
Intermediate
Basic
First language
Fluent

References

On request